Guide to the The Other Economic Summit (TOES) records, 1988-1990 UA 248
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
The Other Economic Summit (TOES) records
1988-1990
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 248
1.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes
The collection consists of background information about The Other Economic Summit (TOES) at Rice University, organizational and press materials for TOES, 1990, publications generated by the meetings, and audio tapes of proceedings.
Biographical / Historical
The Other Economic Summit (TOES), 1990 was the seventh in a series of annual conferences planned to coincide with the G-7, the annual meeting of the world's seven major industrial economies. In 1990 the G-7, also known as the Economic Summit, took place from July 9 to 11 in Houston, Texas. The Other Economic Summit of 1990 took place also in Houston on July 6 through 8.
The founding purpose of The Other Economic Summit in 1984 was to convey to leaders assembled for the Economic Summit, the message that economics "as usual" is leading to a number of undesirable consequences: disrupting cultures, degrading Earth's environment, and undermining people's abilities to join together in common practice to solve problems. From the beginning in 1984, the intention of participants in The Other Economic Summit was to demonstrate that the prevailing exploitative economic policies are not sustainable and are thus ill-suited to the modern world.
The Other Economic Summit of 1990 had as its overall theme "The Voice of the People for a Change," a phrase meant to be understood in two meanings: that the people are demanding change, and that the people, for a change, must be listened to. Each of the three days of TOES '90 had a different topic which was developed by panels and workshops. For the first day the theme was "Global Changes," for the second, "New Perspectives on Ecology and Economy, and for the third, "Democratizing the Economy." Running through the three days were six tracks: sustainable development, environmental and social economic indicators, Houston as microcosm, debt and trade, theories in "alternative" economics, and religious perspectives on economics.
It was intended that position papers on policy alternatives coming out of TOES '90 and collections of thematic papers coming from topical tracks would be published. A draft of the Report and Summary of "The Voice of the People for a Change," edited by Susan Hunt, is included in this collection.
Scope and Contents
Held every year since 1984 immediately before the Economic Summit of Industrialized Nations, The Other Economic Summit (TOES), held in Houston July 6-8, 1990, hosted representatives of the world's poorest peoples. This alternative summit focuses on environmental, social, and alternative approaches to economic problems. Collected by one of the principal local organizers, the collection includes background, organizational and press materials, and publications generated by the Summit.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was received 6-14-90 and 7-29-94 from Prentiss Riddle and Susan Hunt.
Index Terms
Subjects
Rice University -- History; Education
Document Types
press releases; memorandums; programs (documents); photographs; newsletters; T-shirts; audiotapes
- Series I: Planning and marketing documents, 207735
  - TOES/Paris, July 15, 1989, 207737 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Background material, 1988-90, 207738 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The New Economics… Feb. 1989, 207739 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Financial support request, April 1990, 207740 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Outreach ideas/contacts, 1989-90, 207741 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Media lists/contacts, 207742 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Host Committee, 1990, 207743 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Site selection, 1990, 207744 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Communiques/correspondence, April-Winter 1990, 207745 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Advertisements, 207746 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Program prospectus, 207747 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Speakers/participants, 207748 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Schedules, 207749 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Information packet, July 1990, 207750 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Registration materials, 207751 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Media-press releases, 207752 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newsclips, 207753 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - TOES '90: "The Voice of the People for a Change; Report and Summary" draft, 207754 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Final declaration, July 8, 1990, 207755 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, 207756 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - TOES/NA newsletter, 1988-90, 207757 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Related publications, 207758 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2 t-shirts, 207759 (Box 2, Folder -)
- Series II: Audiotapes, 207736
  - Audio tape information and 19 audio tapes of panel discussions, 207760 (Box 2, Folder 4)